<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Dutch remonstrance concerning the proceedings and practices of John de Witt, pensionary, and Ruwaert van Putten, his brother, with others of that faction drawn up by a person of eminency there, and printed at the Hague ; and translated out of Dutch, August the 30th, 1672.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7327</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11799909</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11799909</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49360</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37097)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49360)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 27:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Dutch remonstrance concerning the proceedings and practices of John de Witt, pensionary, and Ruwaert van Putten, his brother, with others of that faction drawn up by a person of eminency there, and printed at the Hague ; and translated out of Dutch, August the 30th, 1672.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. and B.G. and are to be sold by R.C. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1672]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cornelis de Witt was governor of Putten in 1672.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Columbia University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Witt, Johan de, 1625-1672.</term>
               <term>Witt, Cornelis de, 1623-1672.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  1648-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49360:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49360:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:49360:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:49360:2"/> THE Dutch Remonſtrance Concerning the Proceedings and Practices OF <hi>JOHN DE WITT</hi> Penſionary, AND <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>WAERT VAN P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TTEN</hi> his Brother, with others of that FACTION.</p>
            <p>Drawn up by a Perſon of Eminency there, and Printed at the HAGUE.</p>
            <p>And Tranſlated out of Dutch, <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 30th. 1672.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>S.</hi> and <hi>B. G.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>R. C.</hi> over againſt the <hi>Globe</hi> in <hi>Little Brittain.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49360:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49360:3"/>
            <head>THE DUTCH Remonſtrate, &amp;c. Tranſlated out of Dutch.</head>
            <p>EVery one not without Reaſon, ſtands amazed, not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel to apprehend how it is poſsible that in leſs than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty days, the King of <hi>France</hi> ſhould ſubdue above forty Cities and eminent Fortreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; formerly belonging to this State.</p>
            <p>A diſgrace to our Nation, and a blot ſo great that it is never to be waſhed off
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49360:4"/> from the not ſufficiently famous <hi>Bata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet if the Reader pleaſes, ſeriouſly to conſider the following Relation: I doubt not but he will in ſome meaſure be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>My Opinion then is, that the King of <hi>France</hi> did not make ſo great a Progreſs purely by force of Arms, but by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence and aſsiſtance of ſome Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of this Country; (Oh that they had never been ſo!) who being bought thereto, inſtead of Fathers, became Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of our Native Country, which to demonſtrate clearly we are to conſider,</p>
            <p>That the King of <hi>France</hi> did no way ſurpriſe us, but gave us ſufficient warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before hand; as well with words to our Ambaſſadors, as in deeds with his great preparations made by him, beyond any example, through his whole Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; as alſo by his Majeſties erecting ſeveral unheard of Magazines, as well in his own Realm as without, nay on our Fronties at <hi>Nuys.</hi> The preparations
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49360:4"/> whereof were ſo great, that an experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced Officer, who hath borne great Commands in the <hi>German</hi> Wars, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo under the King of <hi>Sweden, Denmark,</hi> and other Princes, coming to Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Lord of <hi>Amerongen,</hi> who at that time was on the behalf of this State at <hi>Colen,</hi> takeing an oportunity to view the forementioned Magazine, declared to me at his return, that he had never ſeen nor heard of the like; believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be ſufficient to contain Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and Amunition enough for two, nay three hundred thouſand men.</p>
            <p>That he could not ſee this State was concerned thereat, asking moreover, if they did not intend to defend their Country; becauſe they made ſuch ſmall preparations for the defence thereof; that the Aſhes ought to be ſtirred, and the Fire extinguiſhed, before the flame grew too big.</p>
            <p>I confeſs that at that time I little regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this ſaying, becauſe according to my Duty I cenſured favourably and expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49360:5"/> nothing but good, and faithfulneſs from our Governors; but I have by the ſorrowful event, found that I might not without a good Argument, have conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to the forementioned Officers opinion.</p>
            <p>For who knowes not that the firſt care of a Governor for the defence of his Country ought to conſiſt,</p>
            <p>In erecting ſufficient Magazines, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of Towns and Caſtles?</p>
            <p>Furniſhing the ſame Towns and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes with valliant and faithful Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Commanders, ſufficient Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Trenches and Amunition for War, and eſpecially to deprive the Enemy of as much Amunition and Men as poſsible. But let us examine whether any of all theſe things were done with vigor and we ſhall to our ſorrow &amp; irreparable loſs and diſgrace rather find the contrary to have been acted by the wicked &amp; ſtrange directions of thoſe corrupt Governors: for notwithſtanding it was well known that at the beginning of the King of <hi>France</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49360:5"/> his preparations for War, that there ſcarce was any <hi>Saltpeeter</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> but what was in the hands of the <hi>Netherland-Eaſt-India</hi> Company; and notwithſtanding it was proffered the State by the ſaid Company yet they refuſed the ſame, and rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that it ſhould be ſent to <hi>France,</hi> and ſo ſerve as a knife to cut the throat of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> at once: which was not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, for beſides that, (inſtead of publiſhing edicts to prevent the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of Amuniton to the Enemy which ought to have been their chief care) they incouraged and maintained the ſending of all neceſſaries for War to the Enemy: of the truth whereof every one may be aſſured, ſince it may be heard from the mouth of the Lord <hi>Jucchen</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Weſel,</hi> yet living in the <hi>Hague;</hi> that his excellency about four or five Months ago, being adviſed in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by a Loyal Subject, that four Ships laden with Powder and Shot and other Amuntion for War were coming up the <hi>Rhine,</hi> to paſs by <hi>Weſel,</hi> adding moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49360:6"/> the Marchants names, that had ſold and bought it, where it was Laden, what Powder-mill the Powder came from, and from whom the other Stores &amp;c. and that the Maſter of the Ship had a Paſport for <hi>Colen,</hi> nay that it was to be carried to <hi>Nuys,</hi> into the French Magazine; adviſing him alſo that by vertue of a certain Order, (ſent to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency ſome years ago, that if the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> ſhould make any Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) he would pleaſe to ſtop the ſaid ſhips; whereupon going himſelf to the <hi>Rhine,</hi> ask't whether any perſons had ſeen ſuch ſhips paſs by as were mentioned in his Letter of advice; (becauſe this is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable buſineſs, I think it will not ſeem amiſs to give an account of the circumſtances thereof) when one of the ſtanders by anſwering ſaid, that two ſuch like ſhips were paſt by and gone up higher, that they were laden with Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Shot and other Amunition, which inſtead of being unladen at <hi>Colen</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Paſtport, were carried
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49360:6"/> and put into the French Magazine at <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ys:</hi> that he had this account from one of the Maſters of the Veſſels that were returned from thence very much diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented that he had been forced to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade contrary to his Paſtport.</p>
            <p>The Governor hereupon ſending for the forementioned Maſter of the Veſſel and having underſtood the truth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the forementioned relation from his own mouth, moreover that there was a third Veſſel laden with the ſame ſort of goods was yet below <hi>Weſel,</hi> and coming up the <hi>Rhine.</hi> Whereupon ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing till the evening, and not ſeeing the ſaid ſhip, the Governor fearing that ſhe might paſs by in the night, ſent ſome Muſqueteers thither, ſtrictly Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to enter and ſtay in the Veſſel till it ſhould come up to the City, and be ſearched by his Excellency. Who on the following day examining the ſaid Ship, found the ſame to be laden as before; when taking the Paſtport from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, he immediately cauſed it to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49360:7"/> Coppied, and keeping the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, ſent the Coppy with the Poſt, who went away that day, or elſe an expreſs had been ſent to the State, or Counſel of State, whom he informed in a letter, all what had happened, and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired ſpeedy order how he ſhould Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern himſelf in this affair.</p>
            <p>There was at that time but little Powder and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot in <hi>Weſel,</hi> ſo that the Governor was not a little rejoyced, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that by this opportunity the City would be well provided at a ſmall charge to the Country.</p>
            <p>But inſtead that the ſaid ſhip ſhould unlade there; the Governor received an order ſigned by the Secretary, that he ſhould not only free the Veſſel which he had ſtopt, but alſo permit all ſhips that had ſuch Paſtports to paſs freely and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moleſted on their way, which his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency immediately condeſcended to.</p>
            <p>Two dayes after paſt by another Ship that had twice as much Amunition aboard her as one of the former, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49360:7"/> from time to time ſeveral others of the ſame nature ſteering the ſame courſe.</p>
            <p>Whileſt the Governor from that time forward ſolicited the Counſel, that the City <hi>Weſel,</hi> being ſo conſiderable a Town and of ſuch great conſequence to the State, ought to have 6000. men in Garriſon, and ſufficient trenches and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition: all which the Governor of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times requeſted in his Letters to the Counſel of State, who at laſt gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for the making of Trenches about the ſaid City, and furniſhing the ſame with all manner of neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>But inſtead of putting a Garriſon of 6000 men into the ſame, they drew immediately thirteen Troops of Horſe, and twelve Companies of Foot, all ſtout and able men out of it, and put a few Companies, conſiſting the greateſt part of unexperienced youths in the ſtead; of which the Governor hath often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained: and to ſecure this conſiderable City the more to the Enemy, they (under pretence that the Governor <hi>Jucchen</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49360:8"/> ſhould come and give their High and and Mighties an account in Perſon in the <hi>Hague)</hi> put in another Governor: and how honourably he hath carried himſelf in the defence of that City appears by the event, <hi>Exitus acta probant.</hi> The like pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence they had to turn out other Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, as appears chiefly by Colonel <hi>D'oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery</hi> an Iriſh man, and a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, whoſe Villanies and Traiterous actions, have been manifeſted formerly in his ſer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>vices under other Princes And one whoſe correſpondence with the Enemy, and notorious Treaſons concerning the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of <hi>Rynberk</hi> are at large related, in a certain paper delivered by the Captains <hi>Vytenbogaert,</hi> and Clark to his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the Counſel of State, and alſo in a certain apology of the Governor <hi>Baſſem,</hi> and a Comment on the letter from <hi>Tondlemonde,</hi> all extant in Print, to which I refer you; wherein alſo you have an account how that the Garriſons of the City <hi>Ryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berk</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49360:8"/> (notwithſtanding it was ſo conſiderable a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs to this State,) were not ſufficient to defend half the Counterſharps: and therefore might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily (by the Treachery of <hi>D'oſſery,</hi> and the falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Governor <hi>Beſſem)</hi> be conquered by the Enemies. And indeed this <hi>D'oſſery</hi> following for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth the examples of the Honourable Lords and Overſeers of this forementioned work, in their counterfeit fatherly care) behaved himſelf no doubt ſo honourably in the defence of this City, that he well deſerved a triumphant Gallows of a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable height, not only his own falſneſs, but becauſe ſo many Loyal Officers which undoubtedly were in Garriſon there, were deluded by his baſe deſignes and treacheries to their utter ruine.</p>
            <p>And for the better carrying on of theſe Traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous courſes, three Regiments more were ſent to <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> after it was ſufficiently provided, ſo that in all probability the Enemy (finding that place ſo fortifyed) ſhould paſs by there, and come firſt to <hi>Rynberk</hi> and <hi>Weſel.</hi> At the ſame time when the newes came to an Aſſembly of a Province now in the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies poſſeſſion, that there were three Regiments more put into <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> it was ſaid, that his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had writ in a letter. that he did much wonder, that ſuch an extraordinary care was taken for that City only, when as it would be more neceſſary to look after other Towns, which were of as great conſequence to the State: this I was informed by a perſon whoſe fortuneit was to be preſent at that Aſſembly.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49360:9"/>
            <p> I alſo heard at that time that a certain Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor being exceedingly troubled, ſaid, what doth all this tend to? I do not like the carriage of affairs, for we are like to loſe our Country for want of men, having 25000 ſhort of what is abſolutely neceſſary.</p>
            <p>And what was the Reaſon?</p>
            <p>They made a great ſhow of raiſing men, but they acted all things contrary.</p>
            <p>For notwithſtanding the firſt levies were made with great trouble out of the country, and we were aſſured that by the many men that were likewiſe raiſed there by others, the Governors of thoſe places had taken an occaſion, ſtrictly to forbid the ſame, inſomuch that we knew, there was not one place, nay not one foot of Land out of our own Dominions left, where we were permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to levy any forces: yet nevertheleſs under a pretence for the good of the Country, it was ſtrictly forbid by an Edict, not to raiſe any men within our Dominions, but in ſuch places where we knew before, there was not a man to be had?</p>
            <p>Nay theſe Officers, (which for the moſt part were <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks) knowing the unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of men to ſtay with them, were forced to raiſe two or three times the men that otherwiſe would have ſerved, to the great exhauſting of the publick Treaſures and their own Eſtates: and yet they could not keep ſo many of them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as to make up halfe a Company at their place of Randeſvouz. Whereupon the Captains
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49360:9"/> making a complaint to the Governors, that it was a common practiſe of the Soldiers, to take their mony, and afterwards to deſert their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours; and deſiring that theſe things might be remedied, they ſhrunk up their ſhoulders, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it was not in their power to help it. Theſe diſorders whereupon of beating of Drums within the Country was left off, and the diſcourſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Officers being, that <hi>Holland</hi> had mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny enough, and conſequently might have men at all times.</p>
            <p>The other great Leavies and Treaties with the Forraign Princes, <hi>viz. Brardenburgh, Lunenburgh</hi> and others, were appointed to be againſt that time when they hoped and judged that all things would be loſt: notwithſtanding it might have been ſooner accompliſhed, and more effectually, the Princes themſelves having proffered their Aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>The Ratification of the Treaty being alſo kept cloſe till the laſt hour, deprived our Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors from making a concluſion.</p>
            <p>We may be informed from the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, that were ſent to <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and now Reſiding in the <hi>Hague,</hi> that they received the Ratification at <hi>Hamborough,</hi> not before the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>July</hi> New Stile</p>
            <p>The ſame Lords Ambaſſadors, declare to the whole World, that the States themſelves may juſtly be blamed for the ſo late coming down of the Auxillary Troops. That at firſt his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> was treated withall, as if
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49360:10"/> they would have bought a diſh of Fiſh of him. That afterwards his Highneſs inſtead of being preſt on, adviſed our Ambaſſador to ſtir up his Lords and Maſters, about the furthering of affairs; ſaying moreover, my Lord you have Traitors in your Country, matters are very ill managed there. I am alſo aſſured, and it may likewiſe be heard from the forementioned Ambaſſadors, that the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the Princes of <hi>Lunenburgh,</hi> and <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mſwick</hi> was broke off only upon a difference of 50<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0 Rix dollers.</p>
            <p>But note, they would rather want the favour of thoſe Princes, and the 8007 men which they would have ſent this State.</p>
            <p>What do you think (ſaid one, of the ſame Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors to me not long ſince) if all the Auxiliary Troops had come down in <hi>May,</hi> would the <hi>French men</hi> have gotten into our Country with ſo much eaſe as they have done? But what ſhall we ſay! It was deſigned ſo, Ambaſſadors were ſent to all Princes and Potentates, when we were aſſured that the Army by the unhandſome proceedings of ſome, which ſhall be nameleſs, were all blockt up; and how our Ambaſſadors managed their affairs in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> I ſhall omit to mention. <hi>De Groot</hi> would alſo have made no better end of his Embaſſie in <hi>France,</hi> had he not been ſeconded by his Brother in Law, that honeſt Patriot <hi>Momba.</hi> One man was not ſufficient, therefore we muſt have a ſecond. In ſhort, affairs were well ordered; our Magazines exhauſted, and the Enemies fil'd.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49360:10"/>
            <p> Levies were ordered to be raiſed in ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where we knew it was forbidden and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be performed: And where Auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were proffered, and might be had with eaſe, thoſe were ſlighted, and put off till ſuch time, as we ſuppoſed, they would be needleſs and too late.</p>
            <p>Moſt of the Garriſons, and eminent places, were either very badly, or not at all fortified. Others, which ſhame forced them to ſtrengthen, wanted one thing or other to make them inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for defence; for thoſe that had men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough were unprovided of Trenches and Amuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thoſe which were ſtored with Powder, Shot, and other Neceſſaries, wanted Men. And thoſe Places, which we knew the Enemy would not meddle withal were crouded with with more Men than were needfull. What ſhall we judge of the eracination of the Strong City and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe <hi>de Graffe,</hi> and the Contrivance, that the whole Garriſon marching thither, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Order, were ſurprized by the Enemy, (who undoubtedly had notice thereof) and ſix and twenty of their Colours taken from them. Nay, we may juſtly ſtand amazed to imagine how it is poſſible, that whole Provinces, as <hi>Overyſſel,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> ſhould be delivered up in one day. And whereon depends that Riddle, that the old experienced ſouldiers, which were kept Priſoners in the Churches of the conquered Towns, ſhould not be taken notice of, and yet beat the Drums
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49360:11"/> daily, for new men: ſeeming rather willing to give twenty, nay thirty Gueldres for new and unexperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced men, than for the old ten or twelve, for which they may be ranſomed.</p>
            <p>Who thought ever to have lived to ſee theſe times in our Provinces, That we muſt go begging from door to door for the Horſe men, and permit them to go a way for want of mony, as hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in this Conjuncture in <hi>Gronningen:</hi> from whence I had advice thereof from a perſon, who was an eye witneſs thereto. When God intends to puniſh a Country, he deprives Loyal Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of their Wiſdome, and permits the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to uſe the ſame to the deſtruction thereof.</p>
            <p>A certain Member of the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> not long before the march of the Enemy, diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to one of his Fraternity about the condition, wherein the Magizines were: ſaid that the Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine of <hi>Holland</hi> was ſo well furniſhed, that, though the Wars continued two years, it was ſufficient of it ſelf, without any more ſupplies: and now, when too late, great Complaints were made, that there was no place provided, every one calling for Powder, Shot, and other Amunition for War; and they were directed to Magizines, which from time to time were emptied, and conſequently had nothing left: The ſaid Lord was askt by his Aſſociate, Where that great and well furniſhed Magizine was, of which his Excellency had boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of ſo much not long before: whereupon ſhrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his ſhoulders, he ſaid that his meaning was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49360:11"/> it would ſerve to furniſh <hi>Holland</hi> only; but none of the other Provinces, which this Lord, who a few days ago gave me an account thereof, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cented very ſtrangely.</p>
            <p>Nay, that which is more, our whole Army being before the <hi>Yſſel,</hi> was two dayes before <hi>Whitſontide,</hi> ſo ill provided of Powder and Shot that in caſe of an Attacque, they would not have been able to defend themſelves above twenty-four houres.</p>
            <p>Some of the Deputies upon the Report which was on <hi>Whitſon Munday,</hi> that the French had taken <hi>Burick,</hi> coming from <hi>Nimmegen</hi> to ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the Lords Deputies that were in the Feild, for Powder and Shot, received for anſwer, that they could not ſpare them any, which was alſo told me at the ſame time by a Governor of <hi>Nimmegen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Kirk Patrik</hi> Governor of <hi>Hertogenboſh</hi> took better care for his Government: ſending the laſt week a liſt to the Counſel of State, of all things which he wanted.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew that his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> uſed more than ordinary care and endeavours, ſent the Governor (whilſt the City committed to his care was blockt up or beſieged) to fetch Powder, Shot, and Canon, which the ſaid Governor obtained, but then could not find a Veſſel that either would or could undertake to carry the ſame thither, of which the Governor hath made great complaints here to ſeveral perſons. Not whether this Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49360:12"/> was blinded by the orders of his Maſter, that he could not ſee the formentioned defects before, or whether the Overſeers of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries welfare, judged that it was of ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to this State to preſerve this Fortreſs; the Magiſtrates formerly were not of that opinion, but the times change, <hi>Tempora mutantur &amp; nos mutamur in illis,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King of <hi>France</hi> needed not to uſe any force upon the Works, which with ſo much care and labour were made along the <hi>Yſſel,</hi> for a far eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er way was ſhown him to come through the River <hi>Rhine,</hi> and ſo to fall into the heart of our Country.</p>
            <p>To which the Trecherous <hi>Momba,</hi> was no ſmall Inſtrument, who having ſo well ordered that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair beforehand in <hi>France,</hi> with his honeſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>de Groot,</hi> that by what means I know not he was made chief Commander of that part of our Militia which were appointed for the defence of that Station. When this Traitor in ſtead of charging his Regiment to be careful in defending their Poſt, and incouraging them to oppoſe their Enemies, gave orders to march up within a mile from <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megen,</hi> and ſo to leave that Station.</p>
            <p>Which when told to his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who extreamly wondred thereat, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Order was immediately ſent, that they ſhould inſtantly draw down to the forementioned Station again, and endeavour by all means poſſible to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ſame.</p>
            <p>But before they could approach the ſame, the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49360:12"/> Enemy was above half over the <hi>Rhine,</hi> ſo that our forces which were to keep that Station, were as if brought to their ſlaughter, and thoſe of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va</hi> his Regiment moſt of them ſlain; as a Lieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant under the Lievtenant Colonel of this Regiment informed me, as he was coming along with twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eight men which he had pickt up from ſeveral companies, after the paſſage through the <hi>Rhine</hi> was opened to the Enemy.</p>
            <q>Et hinc nobis hodiernae illae Lacrimae.</q>
            <p>Now whether that great Favorite of the Enemies can by means of his correſpondence, free his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Law <hi>Momba,</hi> from the puniſhment due to him for the horrid ſlaughter occaſioned by his means, and for betraying of our Native Country, the time will learn us. But we hope that his Conſcience will ſo check him for his own Villanies, that he will not think of acting any more; if it be poſſible for a Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py to leave off hopping.</p>
            <p>One of the Lords Deputies of the Feild (as I was told by an eminent member of their excellencies the High and Mighty States of <hi>Holland</hi> being askt how affairs were ordered, that ſuch ſmall endeavors were uſed to oppoſe the Enemy, he anſwered, that he could give no other Reaſon, but that they had no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret correſpondence to give them any account of the Enemies deſignes, of which they were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant.</p>
            <p>But this Brother, and his accomplices, had too much knowledge of the Enemies deſignes, and were too much concerned therewith.</p>
            <p>For as I am informed, <hi>Momba</hi> would endeavour to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49360:13"/> clear himſelf by the letters from the forementioned Lord: And undoubtedly that was the Reaſon that when his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the Enemy ought to be oppoſed ſometimes in one, and then in another place (to which there then preſented good oportunities) and deſiring hereon the advice or order of the Lord Deputies, he never could get any thing elſe from them, but ſhrink up ſhoulders, and many expreſſions of difficulties, never conſenting, nor abſolutely diſapproving of his Highneſs propoſals; but all things in ſuſpence, tyed up as it were his Highneſſes hands, that he could not do any thing in the defence of our Native Country.</p>
            <p>Every one may juſtly ſtand amazed, to conſider how it is poſſible that all things ſhould be thus ſtrangely caryed, when there were &amp; are ſtill ſo many Loyal Governors at the Helm. For my part, I can ſatisfie my ſelf, when I think on the wonderful Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of Officers, and ſtrange Government which hath been of late: to conſider the power and ſway which that Great, and I muſt confeſs moſt Wiſe Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionary (I could wiſh to God that his wiſdome had been imployed for the good of the Country) <hi>John de Witt</hi> bore during the time of his being Penſionary.</p>
            <p>Hath not he under a pretence of freedom brought us into the greateſt ſlavery of the World? Were his intentions from the beginning till the laſt ought elſe? And did his malitious governing tend to any other end, then to root out and diminiſh the luſtre of that illuſtrious houſe of <hi>Orange</hi> and <hi>Naſsaw?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is there any one perſon that can be ſaid to be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant thereof? Can there be a greater inſtitution
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49360:13"/> of ſlavery thought on in the World then to force the whole State, as it were againſt their Conſciences, to ſuppreſs the Prince of <hi>Orange?</hi> (whoſe predeceſſors of bleſſed Memory, may, next to God only be ſaid to have brought us to this our freedome, with great effuſion of bloud and vaſt expence of mony). Nay to oblige themſelves thereto by Oath. We become ſlaves when we are deprived of our Liberty, but ſlaves of ſlaves, nay ſlaves of ſin, when we are prevented from doing of good, and forced by an Oath to do evil. No Governors were admitted to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency but with taking this Oath; and ſo in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Office, were forced to make themſelves guilty of ſo abominable, and before God and the World, horrid ſin of ingratitude, a ſin which not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carries ſo many unheard of Oaths along with it, but is alſo the occaſion of ſo great effuſion of blood in our native Country. A ſin which can and may be ſaid to have given the Almighty God ſufficient reaſon ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to deprive us again of our ſo dear bought free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And bring us to greater ſlavery than ever we were in before. What man how prudent ſoever he be, can apprehend how it is poſſible that one man ſhould infect and poyſon a whole State, wherein there are ſo many wiſe, honourable, and Loyal Regents and Lords, to oblige the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves &amp; their ſucceſſors as much as in them lay, by an Oath, to ſuch a ruinous and ever crying ſin of ingratitude? And yet nevertheleſs it was done, for not above 8 or 10 days before the ſtrange Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, the Pentionary of <hi>Harlem</hi> was forced at the Court, to ſwear to the forementioned perpetual E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. Thus to renew &amp; increaſe the crying and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guilty
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49360:14"/> ſin of our Country. I tremble when I remember that ſome years ago I accidentally lighted on a Book, wherein, inſtead of mentioning the vertues of the praiſe worthy and never ſufficiently famous Princes of <hi>Orange,</hi> ſtood written with an accurſed and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velliſh pen, that there were no vertues of the Princes to boaſt of, but their vices, as Whoring, Adultery, Drunkning and the like, were at large deſcribed and attributed to every Prince? Who doth not ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed at the hearing hereof, and the more when they know that this was not only ſold publickly, but was alſo licenſed and Printed with Authority from the State? The Councellor-Pentionary had ſufficiently examined the ſame and ſupplyed all the defects; and eſteemed the writer hereof as a Loyal Subject, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him the defender of the Countries freedome. But if any thing in that nature had been done to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of that long <hi>John,</hi> or ought had been writ of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Relations, would not the writer thereof have been perſecuted with fire and ſword, and the printed paper or book immediately taken and burnt? What hath not this grand deſigner with the help of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complices and hired ſlaves, which he rewarded by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them ſeveral offices done to execute his treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and wicked deſignes? See farther. No ſooner were the keys of our native Country (always ſo highly eſteemed and preſerved with great care and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection) villainouſly given into the hands of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, but we began to help him to open the Gates alſo. Who could ever dream of ſuch actions? No Books afford the like example. <hi>Peter de Groot</hi> that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured and diſhonorable wretch, is to make Peace.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49360:14"/>
            <p> To which purpoſe he had a blank Commiſſion from the whole State, (without any Inſtructions according to which he might govern himſelf) to treat with the Enemy; and, to ſpeak plain, to make an abſolute agreement for our dear bought Freedom, Religion, and Native Countrey.</p>
            <p>It would ſooner have ſeemed to me and all the World, a Fable than a truth: had it not appeared plainly out of the printed Letter ſent from the Lords the States of <hi>Zealand,</hi> who manifeſted their Fidelity and great fatherly care, and alſo declared, That not without great reaſon they could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſuch an unlimited power as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Groot</hi> had given him; That it was an unheard of thing in the Government of this Countrey <hi>(ipſiſsima verba Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolae)</hi> to give full power to a deputed perſon, to treat with a Potentate; but much leſs with a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Enemy: Moreover, ſaying plainly, that they <hi>(Nota bene)</hi> juſtly ſuſpected this contrary way of acting, and that it gave them an apprehenſion that the Enemy would thereby be encouraged to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch conditions to ſuch Deputy, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can nor muſt be treated of, <hi>viz.</hi> their Religion, Freedom, and the lawful Government of theſe Countreys.</p>
            <p>And how the forementioned three points would have been maintained by ſuch a Deputy, who is a notorious Atheiſt, a Slave to the Enemy, bought to the deſtruction of our whole Government, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one may eaſily judg. Juſt at the time when this Commiſſion was finiſhed, and <hi>de Groot</hi> yet in the <hi>Hague</hi> ready on his departure, I had the honor
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49360:15"/> to ſpeak with one of my very good friends and a member of the High and Mighty States of <hi>Holland,</hi> who on my curious queſtion of <hi>What News?</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his countenance (as if things did not go ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his mind) was pleaſed to ſay: We ſhall in ſhort have a <hi>Peace,</hi> but I fear <hi>a ſorrowful one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Groot</hi> goeth to the King of <hi>France,</hi> and hath <hi>plien pouvoir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When asking amazedly, <hi>How will it be then?</hi> His Excellency replied. There is a lank Charter to be laid before the King, and His Majeſty is to write.</p>
            <p>On which I anſwer'd, Then <hi>de Groot</hi> is a <hi>Great Prophet;</hi> for this morning a certain Lord inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, (as indeed it was true) that the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned <hi>de Groot</hi> about three Months before, diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with him the ſaid Lord, ſaying that our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Countrey was threatned with a great and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible War: <hi>De Groot</hi> anſwering, ſaid, Piſh! piſh! I do not ſee any ſuch great difficulty therein; I do believe that the King of <hi>France</hi> will at the firſt take ſome of our Cities, which we cannot hinder him from, but <hi>(Nota)</hi> I, I <hi>de Groot</hi> (ſtriking on his breaſt) will make Peace with the King of <hi>France</hi> in the field about three Months hence.</p>
            <p>And obſerve the time wherein he received his forementioned Commiſſion, was about ſo long after.</p>
            <p>The Lord hereupon diſcourſing liberally with me, ſaid, That he believed the ſame; becauſe <hi>de Groot</hi> was a perſon who was exceedingly ſelf-opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionated; and that not long ago, (not naming the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49360:15"/> time, which I gueſt at by his words) he had told his Excellency himſelf, that he ſhould certainly conclude a Peace; adding moreover, that though we ſhould loſe, and add a pearl to his Crown by this Peace: yet if we examined the prerogatives and benefits which <hi>Holland</hi> ſhould reap from it, we would not account our loſs ſo great.</p>
            <p>Though this Lord would not favour me with an explanation of the aforeſaid prerogative; yet I ſuppoſe in all likelihood that his chiefeſt aim was that <hi>Holland</hi> ſhould then be ſeparated from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther United Provinces, and freed as it were from that heavy burthen, as they are pleaſed to call it.</p>
            <p>And beſides, that then they would be freed from all fears that His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> at any time ſhould be made <hi>Stadtholder</hi> of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince.</p>
            <p>One would think it ſtrange how it is poſſible, that any men ſhould be tranſported to ſuch imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations: But,</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Quid non mortalia pectora cogis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auri ſacra fames?</hi>—</l>
            </q>
            <p>He was always more for the <hi>French,</hi> than the <hi>Princes</hi> Intereſt.</p>
            <p>This was the reaſon why the Council Penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, in the time of the War with <hi>Munſter,</hi> durſt propoſe in a full Aſſembly, to make the Duke of <hi>Turenne</hi> Captain General over our Militia.</p>
            <p>Ambitious is our Enemy; and full of ambition are alſo thoſe Subjects; rather deſiring to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49360:16"/> by a <hi>King</hi> than a <hi>Prince.</hi> But ſee how mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous is the providence of the Almighty!</p>
            <p>Juſt when our State was in greateſt danger, and tottering ready to fall down; the appearance of our deliverance was neareſt at hand: for it pleaſed God juſt at that time to throw down that <hi>Great</hi> and ſubtil Deſigner (which had thus long uſurped more authority, than ever was aimed at by any of our Princes) and immediately cauſed the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> unanimouſly by all the Inhabitants of thoſe Countreys, to be proclaimed <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adtholder of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Zealand and Weſt-Fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſland,</hi> and to reſtore to him all thoſe Dignities which his Predeceſſors of Glorious Memory ever enjoyed.</p>
            <p>That Great God grant alſo, that as by means of His Predeceſſors, with the expenſe of their eſtates and effuſion of blood, the Body of the United Provinces was framed, and as long as they reigned kept in a good order: the disjoyned Members may by his valour and conduct (wherein we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God to aſſiſt him, and to free him from evil counſel, and bleſs him more and more daily) be united again.</p>
            <p>I do certainly believe that many of our Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and alſo all good Patriots will judg it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to find out all thoſe Governors which are guilty of betraying our Native Countrey, and by ſome ſevere puniſhment inflicted on them and their Inſtruments, as <hi>Momba, D'Oſſery,</hi> and other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, Commanders, Captains and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and make them an example to others.</p>
            <p>But as to the later part, I do not altogether ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49360:16"/> of their opinion; nevertheleſs, with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to better judgments, my ſentiment onely is, that it would be convenient to make a ſtrict enquiry into the Camp proceeding of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, and ſuch as bore the chiefeſt commands, and had the charge of defending Cities and Fortreſſes, as <hi>Momba, Van Zanten, Baſſem, D'oſſery,</hi> and the like: as alſo thoſe perſons, whether Officers or others, that have been aſſiſting to the Governors in executing of their treacheries, and had daily cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the Enemy.</p>
            <p>And by puniſhing all ſuch perſons ſeverely, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their demerits, make them examples to others.</p>
            <p>But there ought not ſo particular a regard to be taken of other Captains and meaner Officers, who cannot be ſaid to have had the leſt knowledg of their unfaithful Governors deſigns: and would have undoubtedly behaved themſelves moſt loyal, had they been encouraged thereto by their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, and not been deluded to act thoſe things which they were made believe would be for the benefit of the countrey, but proved prejudicial; for which if any ſhould be puniſhed, moſt of all the Captains and other Officers in what Garriſon ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, would be lyable thereto. And thoſe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains which ſhould be puniſhed more than others, would be unjuſtly dealt withall: or the State con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to an execution of ſo many honeſt people, which heretofore have behaved themſelves like loyal Souldiers for the defenſe of their countrey<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and now onely brought thereto by the trecherous
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49360:17"/> (though ſeeming fair) pretences and deluſions of their baſe Governors.</p>
            <p>We have alſo oftentimes ſeen that Military per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and other inferior Officers, being accuſed of ſome committed abuſes, and freed from their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments out of a particular favour; have taken an occaſion in all future opportunities to uſe more than ordinary endeavours for the good and benefit of the State: Of which there are many examples, whereof one is manifeſted at this time in Captain <hi>Buket.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould alſo judg, that ſome means might be found out who amongſt the Regents is guilty of this High Treaſon, and conſequently deſerving of puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially if we conſider thoſe Maxims that are uſed, and alſo neceſſary in our Government: that is, That onely a few are to be admitted into the Council for private concerns, either one out of every Province, or elſe more or leſs according as the buſineſs requires. Beſides which perſons, none may have the leſt knowledge of things of greateſt conſequence, eſpecially in times of War, when the wellfare of the State doth not a little depend, that the Regents deſigns againſt the Enemy may be kept ſecret, and not divulged and brought to the ears of the Enemy. Which private conſultations were well obſerved by the Council Penſionary, who permitted his creatures to be of the Privy Council, and excluded ſeveral good Patriots, who his Excellency judged would oppoſe him in the carrying on of his wicked deſigns: and thoſe which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49360:17"/> he could not exclude, he wrought ſo upon, that he made them to vote ſuch things as his wiſdom thought fit.</p>
            <p>And therefore thoſe loyal Regents which ſate at the helm, might now eaſily (being under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange)</hi> find out with what malice their wicked Brother Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors have ordered all things to the ruine of our countrey, and the furthering of the Enemies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.</p>
            <p>Whether in their ill care for the Fortreſſes, bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtoring the Mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zins, granting of unlawful Paſsports for the tranſporting Ammunition to the Enemy, bad management and preventing the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Levies, detaining of our Embaſſadors, and ratifications of the Treaties, the ill performance of them: moreover in the ſtrange conduct of their appointed Governors, Commanders, and others; and the like baſe carrying on of affairs.</p>
            <p>For if once the thred be found, the bottom will ſoon be unwound.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all which, my judgment is, that the publick inquiſitions and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ought to be referred, ſince undoubtedly it will be of a dangerous conſequence; partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that by the manifold difficulties which in all appearance would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> true, the Loyal Regents, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our Native countrey, would be prevented from uſing other means, which in this conjuncture of time are more neceſſary to oppoſe the Enemy: And partly, that when the treaſon is found out, the puniſhments muſt neceſſarily follow.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49360:18"/>
            <p> Which my forementioned Opinion I leave to every ones ſerious conſideration: How it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the executing of the puniſhments (which undoubtedly would be inflicted on ſeveral of the ſupremeſt Governors, which have ſo long mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Helm of our Government,) could be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, without fear of great inconvenience to this State, which in this conjuncture muſt by all means poſſible be prevented.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that pleaſe to read the Hiſtory of <hi>Barne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> will find, that it is not to be done without great difficulties, which neceſſarily ought to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and referred till ſome other and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time, when either all things may be buried in Oblivion, or elſe the Traitors condemned to loſe their Heads, for betraying our Native coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as the Lords Magiſtrates ſhall think fit.</p>
            <p>And therefore, is it not abominable that private perſons dare daily preſume to do Juſtice, nay to inflict ſufficient puniſhments on all and every one, whom they do but in the leſt ſuſpect to have been concerned in the ill management of Affairs; which doth no way beſeem them? But we will hope that the prudence of the Lord <hi>Stadtholder</hi> will prevent the ſame for the future.</p>
            <p>I am very ſenſible that many Patriots, by this delay of puniſhing the Traitors, fear that if the treacheries go unpuniſhed, the State will be left in a great Labyrinth, and in danger of being wholly delivered up into the Enemies hands; becauſe when thoſe wicked Traitors being accuſed of their Villanies, and ſeeing as it were their puniſhments
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49360:18"/> before their eyes; they will uſe all means poſſible to make more and more confuſion in the <hi>Financie,</hi> of which there is yet a great complaint, and increaſe all other diſorders, whereby the Enemy may get footing alſo in the remaining Provinces, in hopes that by that means they eſcape their deſerved pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; which fears of the loyal Patriots are not without ſome Reaſons: ſince an eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son was yeſterday pleaſed to tell me, that if in caſe the confuſion in the <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ancie,</hi> and the bad payment of moneys, which by the wicked directions of the Compt Governors hath been ſo long in practiſe, be not ſuddenly remedied, it would prove very prejudicial to the State. On which I anſwered his Excellency, (wherewith alſo, according to my judgment, all Patriots may be ſatisfied) that his Highneſs was not made a <hi>Stadtholder</hi> to catch flies; and though he did not as yet proceed on an inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and ſudden puniſhment of the Traitors: yet we might well think that his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> would, with the help of many loyal Regents, endeavour by all means poſſible to gain an exact knowledg of that malitious governing, which hath reduced our State to ſo deplorable and ſad condition; and that alſo he will take ſuch care that all thoſe Compt Governors ſhall be bereaved of all publick Employments; but eſpecially for ever excluded out of the Privy Council: ſo to prevent all future miſcarriages of Affairs, and ſettle all things in ſuch order, as ſhall be moſt beneficial to the State.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49360:19"/>
            <p> Let us now think on ſome means whereby our Native Countrey may be brought to enjoy its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Freedom, and to know the Light of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which in many of the torn off Members of this State, is already ſufficiently extinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>We have heretofore, by eſtabliſhing that curſed Edict, not onely refuſed to acknowledg our Real Governor and Chief Magiſtrate of our Countrey, to which Nature, and the formerly received Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits obliged, and ſufficiently might have forced us to: but alſo deſpiſed and excluded Him with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Oaths. Oh horrid action!</p>
            <p>Do we not ſee and read, that when we deſpiſe and diſown our juſt and loyal Magiſtrates, that God ſends wicked and tyrannical Regents in their places?</p>
            <p>I gave thee a King in mine anger, and took him away in my wrath. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. 11.</p>
            <p>Did there ever any greater deſtruction happen amongſt any people, than thoſe which had ſhewn themſelves ungrateful to their Princes, and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thoſe to whom they owed their preſervation?</p>
            <p>If any where, then, it may well be ſaid to be here. That God being juſtly incenſed, hath in his wrath given a great part of our Netherlands to a King.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49360:19"/>
            <p> God grant that as that ſin of Ungratefulneſs pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by our Magiſtrates, which hath chiefly occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned a curſe upon our Countrey, is removed by a Miraculous Providence, <hi>viz.</hi> our Magiſtrates ſuddenly revoking that Wicked and perpetual E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict; ſhewing a ſincere ſorrow of that baſe act, to which they were deluded by the wicked directions of the forementioned Compt Governors: he will alſo be pleaſed to remove all other troubles from us. And grant likewiſe, that our Subjects may repent of thoſe horrid and crying ſins, of which they are guilty, and thereby have incurred Gods juſt diſpleaſure.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
